<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Calebs integrity in following the Lord fully, in a sermon preached at St. Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late solemne and publick fast, Novemb: 30th. 1642. By Richard Vines, Mr. of Arts of Magd. Colledge in Camb: and minister of the gospell at Weddington in the county of Warr</title>
            <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E130_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871622</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 23:E130[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Calebs integrity in following the Lord fully, in a sermon preached at St. Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late solemne and publick fast, Novemb: 30th. 1642. By Richard Vines, Mr. of Arts of Magd. Colledge in Camb: and minister of the gospell at Weddington in the county of Warr</title>
                  <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Abel Roper, at the Signe of of [sic] the Sun against St. Dunstans Church in Fleete-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an order to print on verso of first leaf, dated 30 November 1642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XIV, 24 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:156296:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Mercurij,</hi> 30 Novemb: 1642.</head>
            <p>IT is this Day Ordered by the Commons now Aſſembled in Parliament, that M. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ines</hi> ſhall be deſired from this Houſe, to print the Sermon hee preached before this Houſe at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter this Day at the publike Faſt; And it is further Ordered, that he ſhall have the uſuall privledges as others formerly have had, that none ſhall Print or reprint his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but thoſe whom he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen: Elſyng,</hi> Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I Appoint <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to Print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ines.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156296:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CALEBS INTEGRITY In following the LORD fully, IN A Sermon Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets Weſtminster,</hi> Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, at their late ſolemne and publick Faſt, <hi>Novemb:</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1642.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD VINES, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts of <hi>Magd.</hi> Colledge in <hi>Camb:</hi> and Miniſter of the Goſpell at WEDDINGTON in the County of WARR<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Et facere, &amp; pati fortia, Chriſtianum eſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the Signe of of the Sun againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleete-streete.</hi> M. DC. XLII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156296:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156296:2"/>
            <p>HONOR ATISSIMO, GRAVISSIMOQVE SENATVI PARL. DOM. COM. HANC SUAM QUA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEMCUNQUE CONCIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEM HABITAM APVD EVNDEM,</p>
            <p>IN ECCLESIA SAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTAE <hi>MARGARETAE,</hi> APVD <hi>WESTMONASTERIVM,</hi> SOLEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NI, MENSTRUORUM JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JUNIORUM, DIE, <hi>NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEMB.</hi> ULTIMO, ANNO 1642. EX OMNIBVS, QUI SACRIS OPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANTUR, IN AGRO <hi>WARWICENSI,</hi> MINIMUS.</p>
            <p>D. D. D.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARDVS VINES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:156296:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156296:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CALEBS</hi> INTEGRITY In following the LORD fully. <hi>OR</hi> The Patterne of a godly Man, going upon a dangerous ſervice, or at a deſperate point.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>NUMBERS XIV-XXIV.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But my ſervant <hi>Caleb</hi> becauſe he had another Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with him, (or in him) and hath followed me fully, (<hi>Hebr.</hi> hath fulfilled after me) him will I bring into the Land whereinto he went, and his ſeed ſhall poſſeſſe it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Hiſtory whereof this Text <note place="margin">Verſ. 2. &amp; 9. &amp; 11. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is part; is a narrative of one of the murmurings of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, which famous ſinne of theirs is expreſt in ſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of ſtile, being elſewhere called Temptation of God, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> provocation, or imbittering of God, and ſometime rebellion, which is a ſinne incident to a people that are under promife, or in expectation of good from God, and yet withall, ſo incountred
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156296:4"/> with temptations and obſtructions of their hopes, wave after wave, that they cannot unto themſelves by faith reconcile the promiſe, or tenderneſſe of God with his preſent providence and diſpenſation towards them, his foot-ſteps being cloudy, and his hand heavy: whereupon their ſpirits are even by his probationary ſcourges imbittered againſt him, as if he neither regarded his own truth, nor their ſufferings. And God againe is imbittered againſt them for their unbeliefe in him, their jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of him, their diſcontents, thought or vented againſt him; for God would not have the people of his Covenant, becauſe they are in ſtraits, to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion his reſpect to them; no, though they be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Sea, at point of periſhing: But if his preſent hand make them cry, <hi>Alas for the day is great, It is even the time of</hi> Jacobs <hi>trouble</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 30. 7.</note> (and who will not ſhrinke at the firſt putting his feete into cold water) yet to over-beleeve ſence, and adde withall, <hi>but he ſhall be ſaved out of it.</hi> This murmuring was the Tenth, the greateſt, and of the heavieſt conſequence.</p>
            <p>The Tenth, ſo God himſelfe numbers it, who, as he keepes a Booke of every mans particular ſins (as the phraſe of blotting out imports) and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every mans conſcience is a counter part, ſo it appeares hence that he keepes an exact account of our Nationall rebellions and provocations, <hi>Ver. 22. They have tempted me now theſe ten times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt, for beſides that it is after nine, and the repetition of a ſinne makes the latter <hi>eo nomine</hi> the greater, (<hi>Ezra 9. 14. Should we againe breake thy Commandements</hi>) I ſay, <hi>abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> their other
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156296:4"/> murmurings aroſe upon their want of fleſh, bread, water, or ſome diſlikes of ſome particular occonomy of God over them: This ſtrikes at the roote, at <note place="margin">Chap. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. Deut. 1. 20.</note> the throate of all, for now being in <hi>Paran,</hi> or at the Mountaine of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> in the very borders of the Land of their reſt, ready to put in their ſickle to reape the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo many hundred yeares before. They ſo undervalue and diſhonour Gods reſt made over by deede of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe unto them long agone, and now ready to be given by livery and ſeiſin into their hand, that they prefer a ſlaviſh life, nay a grave in <hi>Egypt,</hi> before ſuch an adventure, <hi>would God that we had died in Egypt,</hi> Ver. 2. <hi>Or would God wee had dyed in the wilderneſse,</hi> any grave would ſerve their indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rather then they would put on for this inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and haply they thought (as we ſometimes doe in like caſe) that this Land being in promiſe, it ſhould have dropt into their mouthes, even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their opening them, and not have beene a Land of conqueſt as well as promiſe; for ſo we fancy, that promiſes muſt fulfill themſelves, even though we be not in capacity of them, or contribute not to ſerve Gods command or providence in the way of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them.</p>
            <p>And what was the conſequence? God was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, and in his wrath ſwore an oath excluſive of this people, led them off the borders of the Land a 40. years march in the wilderneſſe, untill all the mutineers (all above twenty yeares old at their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of <hi>Egipt</hi>) fell therein. Upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, not a man of that great people (except <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhuah</hi>) of much above 60. yeares of age came into <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:156296:5"/>
            <p>Now if theſe things be our enſamples, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 6.</note> then it is but laying the ſcene among our ſelves, and the reſult of it will be this; That if after all our other Nationall provocations of God, for which wee have long deſerved, that the hand ſhould write upon the wall, <hi>that God hath numbred our Kingdome and finiſht it.</hi> We ſhould be brought to the borders of that long prayed for reſt from our yoakes and burdens in Church and State, and then prove, as I may ſo ſay, run-awayes from <hi>Edge</hi> Hil, and ſtumble at the threſhold, deſpiſing the offer, cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our former prayers, ſcandalizing our ſelves, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The time is not come, the time the Lords houſe ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>be built,</hi> and ſo wiſh for Captaines that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into <hi>Egipt,</hi> as this people, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. Might wee not feare ſuch another oath of God againſt us, and ſuch another pilgrimage of our ſelves in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our own miſery, untill our carcaſſes were all fallen as theirs.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this mutiny was, Twelve Princes or heads of the Tribes, were ſent out to diſcover the Land, they went, returned, and reported, but theſe Twelve were not all agreed of their verdict, they were ten to two; The ten ſpoke their carnall feares, nothing but walled Townes, warlike people, ſons of <hi>Anak.</hi> the Land indeed is good, but like the garden of the <hi>Heſperides,</hi> Dragons keepe it; not a word or ſillable of Gods covenant, promiſe, or preſence, to counter-ballance or make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement. The people are drawn after them and imbittered, they cry out that God hath betraid their lives, Wives, Children to manifeſt ruine, and to <hi>Egipt</hi> they will backe againe.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:156296:5"/>
            <p>The two, <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> countervoted the ten, <note place="margin">Num. 30. 30, 31.</note> and proteſted. We are not able ſay the ten, we are well able ſaith <hi>Caleb;</hi> they are ſtronger then we ſay the ten, they are bread for us ſay the two; wee are <note place="margin">Cum Cap. 30, 31, 32, 33. Cum. Cap. 14, 8, 9.</note> Piſmires and Graſhoppers to them ſay the ten; the Lord is with us, feare them not ſay the two; they are fenced in with walles, and giants ſay the ten; their ſhadow is departed from them ſay the two; This was the conteſtation, but the Noes carried it, and though <hi>Caleb</hi> and his fellow plyed the people with Gods preſence, power and promiſe, and with the experience they had had of him, yet they got no heate into them, but the heate of inſolency and rage, <hi>All the Congregation bad ſtone them with stones,</hi> Verſ. 10. Spirituall arguments to a carnall heart, are but warme clothes to a dead man; when men have once a prejudice againſt God, as if he would be falſe to them, and thinke their faith in his promiſes will be but a ſnare to ingage them into wayes deſtructive of themſelves, then it's no oyling of a wheele ſo skotcht: for it is a ſure rule, he that hath no faith to make uſe of God, would by no meanes have need of him. When this people ſaw the great worke which God had done upon <hi>Egipt,</hi> then they beleeve; the <note place="margin">Exo. 4 31.</note> faith of a carnall heart is laid up in preſent ſence or evidence of Gods hand; but while the <hi>Anakims</hi> are alive, God is no body to them; a hard heart will not bring up former experiments of God, to charge new dangers in the face, for though ſaith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> you have ſeene ſo much of God already, <hi>yet in this thing yee did not beleeve the Lord your God.</hi> On the <note place="margin">Deut. 1. 31, 32.</note> contrary, <hi>Caleb</hi> values God alone againſt all that can be ſaid, and makes the Giants but Piſmires to his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156296:6"/> faith, by ſetting God by them, of ſuch down-weight is God, to a ſpirit of faith, in that very thing wherein to an unbeleever he doth not ſo much as ſtirre, much leſſe turne the beame.</p>
            <p>So much for the ſurvey of the Suburbs of the Text, whereby you already doe perceive, that here is ſomething that is proper to the Meridian of our owne caſe.</p>
            <p>And now I am at the words, which are an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Caleb</hi> out of the number of them, whom God by oath peremptorily excluded the Land of promiſe for their Rebellion, and therein we have,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods teſtimony of him.</item>
               <item>2. Gods promiſe to him.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <label>1. Gods teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of him.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. He hath fulfilled after me.</item>
                           <item>2. He had another ſpirit with him.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Gods promiſe to him. <hi>Him will bring,</hi> &amp;c. and therein,</item>
               <item>1. The aſſignement of <hi>Calebs</hi> plot, the Land hee ſearched, or that part of it into which he went.</item>
               <item>2. The ground of that promiſe; becauſe <hi>he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſpirit, and hath</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3. The entaile of the promiſe, or the inheritance upon his ſeed. <hi>His ſeed ſhall poſseſſe it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with Gods teſtimony of this ſervant of his, <hi>He hath fulfilled after me,</hi> which after this time you may obſerve to be ſet as a marke of honour upon <note place="margin">Deut. 1. 36 Ioſ. 14 &amp; 6. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note> this man: inſomuch as when his name is named, this character ſirnames him, <hi>Hee that followed mee fully;</hi> in like manner, as that brand ſtickes upon the name of <hi>Ieroboam, Hee that made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156296:6"/>
            <p>I liſt not to vex the words. The Hebrew being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he hath fullfilled after me,</hi> anſwered with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; in the new Teſtament, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Cor. 10. 6. when your obedience is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled:</hi> but I will not ſtand to tub that eare, which will yeeld me no more corne then the Tranſlation hath beaten out. <hi>He hath followed me fally;</hi> as if the Lord had ſaid, he hath ſtuck cloſe to me, and improved the buſineſſe under his hand, howſoever ſucceſleſly as to the people, yet dangerouſly as to himſelfe for my ſake, and managed it to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of my honour, by valuing me, my promiſe, preſence, power, againſt all Objections made by humane wiſedome; or Obſtructions laid by humane power.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee what the Text holds forth unto us, and that honey is beſt, which runnes freely from the combe; we muſt not commit rape or extortion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word of God, a ſinne too frequent in our times, by ſuch as are moſt zealous for their party, for how many doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cauponari verbum Dei,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, daſhing and mixing as Huckſters doe their wares, adulterating the pure word with their owne crude fancies, and ſo uttering and venting it abroad into the world, to the great ſcandall of Scripture it ſelf, godlineſſe, learning and ingenuity.</p>
            <p>The Obſervations that offer themſelves willingly are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That God makes great reckoning of, and gives ſpeciall testimony unto ſuch his ſervants who fulfill after him. <hi>My ſervant</hi> Caleb <hi>hath fullfilled after me.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156296:7"/>
               <item>2. To fulfill after the Lord, proceeds from another ſpirit than the unbeleeving <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are acted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. <hi>He had another ſpirit with him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Such ſhall not looſe by the hand, who out of a right ſpirit doc follow the Lordfully. <hi>Becauſe he had,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>him will I bring into the Land,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, it is not <hi>Calebs</hi> commendation onely, but every mans duty alſo, who beares this ſtile, <hi>My Servant.</hi> You heare that <hi>Solomon</hi> who out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with his wives, tooke in alſo, as I may ſay, Concubines to Gods Temple, is therefore char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, 1 <hi>King. 11. 6. Not to have fulfilled after the Lord;</hi> and <hi>Iehu</hi> who out of compliance with that pollicy which proved fatall to that Kingdome, not caſting out that <hi>Ieroboamiticall</hi> Idolatry in being, is likewiſe charged, 2 <hi>King. 10. 31. Not to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to walke in the Law of the Lord with all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> heart:</hi> both of them are taken as defective in this duty, he that tooke in more, and he that caſt out leſſe then might anſwer the levell of Gods order of worſhip, and judge the ſame in other caſes. For it is plaine by our Saviour his frequent and inſtant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that his people muſt deny, looſe, ſell, forſake, hate all, not onely all ſinne, but all deareſt things of this life, which are lawfull, neceſſary, and (out of the caſe of impediment of our following of Chriſt, and their competition with him) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be ſought or enjoyed, which can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port no leſſe then this duty of <hi>fulfilling after the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are theſe meerly Evangelicall counſels to ſome perfect men, but obligatory of all Chriſtians, otherwiſe that weight could not be laid on, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156296:7"/> is, <hi>Whoſoever doth not this cannot be my Diſciple,</hi> And indeed, as the Philoſopher ſaith of privation, that it is one of the principles of naturall generation; ſo is ſelf-denyall and the whole ſale of all for Chriſt, it is the firſt leſſon, howſoever it be laſt that is well learned, being the onely <hi>removens prohibens,</hi> that which removes all impediments of our fulfilling af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt. And as the times of Chriſt, oppoſite to the inſtitution of the Goſpell did require the incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Point, ſo ours, oppoſite to the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods worſhip to it's native ſimplicity, doe beſpeake the ſame, being ſuch, <hi>In quibus animum firmare oportet constantibus exemplis,</hi> as he in <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this Point, we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What ground-worke is requiſite to be laid in a man, that he may fulfill after the Lord.</item>
               <item>2. What it is to fulfill after him.</item>
               <item>3. Why we ſhould fulfill after him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt of the three, I ſhall acquit it in foure things, of which the ſecond will riſe out of the firſt, the third out of the ſecond, the fourth out of the third.</p>
            <p>1. The firſt and indeed the root of all the reſt, is this, that there be in a man a principle of ſaving faith, cloſing with Chriſt to ſecure the preſent and finall eſtate of the ſoule, or the ground-worke of ſound Regeneration and converſion to God; there may be many workings or gifts of the Spirit of God in and unto men, in whom there is not a ſpirit uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Chriſt, and there is a dogmaticall faith of holding the truth in opinion and aſſent which is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156296:8"/> not juſtifying of the perſon by reception of Chriſt; now there muſt be ſuch a ſpirit, and ſuch a faith as may carry the ſoule out of it ſelfe for ſubſiſtence, and above it ſelfe in operation and working, ſo that God may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whom and unto whom the ſoule doth act, and then it will follow, that he that hath caſt his ſoule on Chriſt by faith, ſecuring the maine eſtate thereof, ſhall the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily caſt away his life, eſtate, &amp;c. in a particular cauſe for him. He that through all the pangs and ſtruglings of the new-birth, diſcouragements at the weight and height of his ſinnes, oppoſitions of reaſonings, deluſions and flatteries of ſelf-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, violence of hell it ſelfe, hath ſhot the maine gulfe and hath landed in Chriſt, ſhall with more facility lay aſide his leſſer, his outward intereſts for him: for it is a terrible thing for the ſtouteſt heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live to looke ſuch a danger in the face, as for ought he knowes may at one blow kill him and damne him, or in a moment, ſend him both to his grave and hell, it makes a man follow the Lord fully, when he obeyes the Commandement by the ſame faith, whereby he receives the ſaving promiſe, and offers up <hi>Iſaac</hi> by the ſame faith, whereby hee got him; that is, to obey and ſuffer by a juſtifying faith, as they, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. whoſe acts there expreſſed, were not moſt of them juſtifying acts, yet done by a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and juſtifying faith, for ſo it is the ſame hand which ſhuts and cloſes upon the gift and opens it ſelf to work. And yet I muſt needs preoccupate an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and grant that <hi>Abraham</hi> who beleeved the maine promiſe without ſtaggering, ſhewed ſome trepidation, when he conceived himſelfe in danger
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156296:8"/> of his life, <hi>They will kill me,</hi> ſaith he; but that is <note place="margin">Gon. 12. 12.</note> but the encountring of ſence with faith, which ſence fights ſore againſt faith, when it is upon it's owne dung-hill, I meane in a ſenſible danger, natures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of itſelfe from a viſible feare may cauſethe pulſe of a Chriſtian which beats truely and ſtrongly in the maine point, <hi>the ſtate of the ſoule,</hi> to intermit and faulter at ſuch a time; but the needle will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the true point againe upon ſelf-recollection, <hi>That godlineſse hath the Promiſes that belong to this life and the life to come:</hi> as for ſuch men whoſe hearts are not ballaſt with grace; no marvell if they ride uncertainly and are up and downe in rough wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for though in faire and eaſie weather they may keepe tune and time, yet it will be no wonder if they ring their bels backward whenthings begin to bee on fire, <hi>Religio religat,</hi> Godlineſſe bindes faſt.</p>
            <p>2. The ſecond is, That a man affect God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and account him his great reward, and this is the immediate effect of ſaving grace and faith, to bring the ſoule into the eſteeme and acceptance of God himſelfe for our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or chiefeſt good; it is true thoſe Promiſes, <hi>I will call for the corne and increaſe it, and will multiply the fruit of the Tree and of the Field,</hi> are bleſſings and benefits of his Covenant, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 29. And <hi>bleſſed are the people that are in ſuch a caſe,</hi> Pſal. 144. 15. but the maine Promiſe of the Covenant is, <hi>I will be their God and they ſhall be my people;</hi> and then ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Ibid. Yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> That which we call <hi>amor amicitie</hi> or <hi>conjugalis</hi> clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with the perſon, and not onely with benefits.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156296:9"/> The firſt Commandement ſhewes that this is the moſt naturall order; firſt, to have God for our God, and then and thence to performe other duties. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility when one is awed from ſinne, or driven to duties by the whip, and mercenarines when one is drawne by meere benefit or reward, are the bane of following the Lord fully: He that parts with ſinne as a ſlave, parts with it and loves it, and will in the calme gather up againe that which hee caſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board in the ſtorme; and hee will performe duties and hate them: He that followes God as a merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary will no longer <hi>uti Deo,</hi> then he can <hi>frui mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> He will uſe him while he can ſerve himſelfe of him. Duties and ſufferings are irkeſome things without that <hi>ſuave condimentum,</hi> the love of God himſelfe. I know the opinion of merit with God or men, ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens ſharpe duties and ſufferings to ſome palats, but that is but <hi>dulce venenum,</hi> a ſweet poyſon to all wee doe, it fruſtrates our very Faſts, <hi>Did yee at all Faſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 7. 5</note> 
               <hi>unto me, even unto me?</hi> Was it not an argument of an excellent ſpirit in <hi>Moſes,</hi> when God offered him the benefit without himſelfe or his preſence, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 2. <hi>I will ſend an Angell before thee, and I will drive out the Canaanites,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>I will not goe up in the midſt of thee;</hi> and this was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſhall but <hi>conſume</hi> thee if I do; what a fair offer was this, and what a reaſon of Gods denyall of his owne preſence was that, and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> could not be content with it; <hi>For if thy preſence goe not with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 25.</note> 
               <hi>me, then carry us not up hence.</hi> Let us be here in the Wildernes under thy Cloud, rather then poſſeſſe a <hi>Canaan</hi> without thee.</p>
            <p>3. The third is, To value Gods intereſts in any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156296:9"/> buſineſſe under our hand, more then our owne, his Goſpell, his cauſe, his glory; and this riſes out of the former; for he that loves God himſelf, above himſelfe, will value Gods intereſt above his owne. It is the property of a ſincere heart to obſerve, what ſhare God may have in any action or duty to which he is called, and to diſtinguiſh and abſtract it from his owne. We have a famous inſtance in <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was offered a private fortune, even by God himſelfe, <hi>I'le make of thee a great Nation,</hi> greater <note place="margin">Numb. 14 12.</note> and mightier then they; no (ſaith he) Lord, thou wilt be a looſer by it, and ſhalt runne the hazard of thy honour; and ſurely as God was diſpleaſed with <hi>Balaam</hi> for going, though hee bad him goe, ſo the Lord would not have taken it ſo kindly of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> if he had taken him upon the offer he made in a time of his heat againſt his people; nothing makes a man eccentricke in his motions ſo much as private reſpects; he that hath an habituate bie-end, hath as it were a nayle in his foot, and though he may goe well enough in ſoft ground, yet hee will halt when he comes in hard way: If ever in any great buſineſſe God did intwiſt his owne intereſt with ours, it is now in our caſe, and if there be any that could bee content to ſit downe in the ſettlement of their liberty and property, without further care of Religion, and to dwell in ſeiled houſes, while the houſe of God <note place="margin">Hag. 1. 4.</note> lyes waſte: let me put them in mind of <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> who being ſeated in their plot, would yet march on to ſee the reſt of the Tribes ſetled, as well as themſelves, before they would ſit down; and ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> if you will not do ſo, <hi>yee have ſinned againſt the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 32. 18, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, and be ſure your ſin will find you out.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:156296:10"/>
            <p>4. The fourth is, To be able to periſh for God, and this riſes out of the former, for he onely can lay himſelfe out for God, that can lay up himſelfe in him: And it is a point of great ability, <hi>I know how to be abaſed, how to hunger, I can doe all things, Phil.</hi> 4. 12. Let no man ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> thou muſt hunger and be abaſed, it is a matter of neceſſity, nay but yee ſee he makes it a point of ability in him, that he can be in a neceſſitous condition; a man ſhall never be quiet nor at point, till he can looſe himſelfe to ſave himſelfe, as Chriſt ſpeakes, and periſh to live, for he ſhall be daunted at every alarum of ill tydings, fearefull of the ſhadow of the Croſſe; every dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in a duty awes him; every frowne of a great man daſtards him, untill hee can periſh in his reputation, and be vile, more vile, yet more vile for God, or <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note> can come to that, <hi>They would not be delivered.</hi> It was the greateſt heart-breaking to <hi>Paul</hi> when his friends in affection to him, would have beſought him out of his owne danger, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 13, 14. And this ground-worke being well laid, you may eaſily ſee how poſſible and probable it is, that ſuch a man ſhould follow the Lord fully, eſpecially in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God and of Religion, wherein many excellent <hi>Romanes</hi> to their Country and true Patriots, prove ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truants and heavy ſlugs.</p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond thing, <hi>viz.</hi> what it is <hi>to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill after the Lord,</hi> or who may be ſaid to doe it? And this I ſhall briefly run through.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. More generally.</item>
               <item>2. More particularly.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. For the more generall explication of this point, <hi>To fullfill after the Lord.</hi> 1. Excludes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156296:10"/> in the Law of God and takes in integrity. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality is either in the negative part of the Law, and that is when a man caſts off ſome ſinnes, and hath ſome other, one at leaſt, <hi>in delicijs;</hi> or in the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative part, when he plowes here, and makes a bawke there, this cannot be following fully, for that conſiſts in integrity of averſion from ſinne, and of converſion to God, <hi>quoad aſſenſum &amp; conatum.</hi> 2. It excludes ſiniſterity of ends, and takes in ſincerity; for the Scripture brands it for an empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of fruit, when a man brings forth fruit to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Iſrael is an empty vine, he brings ſorth fruit to himſelfe.</hi> 3. It excludes lukewarme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and takes in zeale, not that preternaturall heate, miſcalled zeale; for that is a diſeaſe rather then a grace; zeale ſhould eate us up, but not eate up our wiſdome, nor ſhould pride eate up our zeale. 4. It excludes the meere forme of godlineſſe, and takes in power; for forme wants the chiefe dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of holineſſe, which is depth and ſubſtance; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe follow not ſully, that run before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement in outward forme, but walk not after it it in morall piety. 5. It excludes withdrawing and takes in conſtancy, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to follow fully, and goe on to the end, are much at one; he that walkes fully after the Lord, walkes fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally after him. But this fulfilling after the Lord, doth not neceſſarily require legall perfection, as to exclude all ſinne out of the perſon, or his wayes, for we heare of none beſides the two <hi>Adams,</hi> in whom it might be ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is no ſin; though it was ſaid of one, and may be of other true <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there is no guile,</hi> or predominant
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156296:11"/> hypocriſie; Neither doth this fulfilling after the Lord, exclude inequality, and take in the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as neceſſarie in all, for the fullneſſe of two veſſells, doth not infer the equality of them; God hath differently tallented men with grace, parts, meanes, opportunities, and he doth not require him that hath but one tallent, to put forth five.</p>
            <p>2. For the more particular explication of the point, and firſt, who fulfils after the Lord in duties of obedience, and that is when a man walkes,</p>
            <p>1, Univerſally in compliance of heart and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to the whole rule, clipping off induſtriouſly no part of that ſervice which beares Gods ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription upon it, though it may be to him harſh and unpleaſant, yet the command of God ſhall both awe and draw the heart unto it, for that word, <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> makes every Thou ſhalt of his, and every Thou ſhalt not, acceptable to a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, and this is to walke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fully.</p>
            <p>2. Freely, though no rod be holden over us, the Laws curſe is the impreſt ſhilling to force a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile ſpirit, but the love of God is the byas of a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiere. Grace is that whereby God is free in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to us, and grace is that which makes our hearts free in obedience to him, and this freeneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will be moſt ſeene, when there are moſt rubs in the way; for then he that moves by outward poyſes will ſtick and be dull: as when a bowle runs up hill every rub ſluggs it, but when it goes downe hill a rub quickens it; a free ſpirit is enkindled by that which quencheth another man.</p>
            <p>3. Satisfied in part with duty, and with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſincerity and exerciſe of his graces there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156296:11"/> though ſucceſſe anſwer not; what a joyfull man was <hi>David</hi> when he and his people had offered ſo willingly the materialls of a Temple, though he might not build it, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. What pleaſure tooke <hi>Paul</hi> in infirmities and reproaches for Chriſt, when the ſtrength of Chriſt was <hi>perfected in his weakeneſſe, 2 Cor.</hi> 12. 10. And this is that ſatisfaction wherein a good conſcience finds ſome reſt, when a man can pray, can beleeve, waite and ſpeake for God, though the ſucceſſe and event anſwer not his duties or deſires, a good heart is loaden with the very burden of duty, and finds eaſe when it is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely diſcharged, let the iſſue be as it will.</p>
            <p>4. Independent upon, and unreſpective unto the eye and account of men, and that, 1. Though equalls intereſſed as well as he doe deſert him, as the ten did <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua.</hi> 2. Though the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple miſconſtrue him, as theſe did them; hee that walkes by mens countenance or eye, ſteeres by a Planet, and not the Pole-Star.</p>
            <p>2. To fulfill after the Lord when impediments lye in our way, and croſſe winds carry us from the Port, is,</p>
            <p>1. To reckon upon God with us, againſt all mountaines of oppoſition, ſo <hi>Caleb, The Lord is with us, feare them not.</hi> Thus the Prophet animated his man being in feare, and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his Subjects, <hi>There be more with us then with him,</hi> yet had he none but <note place="margin">2 King 6. 16. 2. Chro. 32. 7.</note> God to recken on, and the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> had a hundred foureſcore and five thouſand at leaſt; ſuch is this God of ours, who ſaith, <hi>Shall I bring to the birth, and not cauſe to bring forth, Iſa.</hi> 66. 9. who promiſeth <hi>Iacob</hi> the worme, that he ſhall be his inſtrument to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156296:12"/> 
               <hi>thraſh mountaines to duſt, Iſa</hi> 41. 14, 15. and what compariſon betweene a worme and a mountaine; what other reaſon is given of the breaking in peeces of all confederacies and aſſociations againſt the Church, but only this, <hi>For Immanuel, Iſa</hi> 8. 10. and it might teach all the world, to ſay when they ſet againſt God, <hi>ſi collidimus frangimur,</hi> as the earthen pot againſt the iron rod breakes not the iron, but is it ſelfe broken.</p>
            <p>2. To ſtand firme, by ſetting one foote upon the experiences we have had of God, and the other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his promiſes yet in expectation; for our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of him, we may argue from his opening of the red Sea, to his opening of <hi>Iordan.</hi> He that ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sea to bring us into this wilderneſſe, will ſurely open a River to let us out. And for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to his people, they will eate their way over all Alpes of oppoſition, God will be the midwife of them to deliver them of their wombe, as it's ſaid, <hi>He hath fulfilled with his hands, that which he ſpake with his mouth.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 6. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3. To fulfill after the Lord, being in incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces inward, outward, is,</p>
            <p>1. When a man prefers not a quiet <hi>Egipt,</hi> before a troubleſome and hazardous adventure upon the Land promiſed; He will never repent of his choyce of God, nor of his ingagements to his cauſe, though he ſuffer for it, and loſe by it, he will never ſay, would God I had died in <hi>Egipt,</hi> nor ſound for a parley with the world and ſinne, nor ſound a retreat to his heart, to march away from the cauſe or work of the Lord.</p>
            <p>2. When we miſconſter not Gods intention and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156296:12"/> meaning towards us, nor put a falſe gloſſe upon his hand that goeth forth againſt us, like theſe rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten-hearted <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that cryed God would betray them; it is hard when his covenant, truth and love, cannot vindicate him from all poſſibility of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood towards us, or forgetfullneſſe of us. Keepe up good thoughts of God; that if he bring us not into <hi>Canaan</hi> at the fore-doore, yet after he hath led us about to humble our pride, he will bring us in at the poſterne, as he did this people; and if he ſave not <hi>Ionah</hi> by the Marriners, he may ſave him by the Whale that ſwallowes him.</p>
            <p>3. The third thing is, why his people ſhould fulfill after the Lord; in which I will be briefe, for <hi>Eliah</hi> his reaſon is enough, <hi>If the Lord be God follow</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18. 21.</note> 
               <hi>him,</hi> for all attractives are in him, all remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, all reſtoratives, and he expects it of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, commends it in them, and rewards it to them: He expects it, I know <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaith God, that he will doe ſo and ſo: He commends it, as here he doth <hi>Caleb, he followed me fully:</hi> He rewards it, as here he promiſeth, and afterward performed to <hi>Caleb,</hi> and generally they that follow the Lord home.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Shall ſee more of him.</item>
               <item>2. Receive more from him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. They ſhall ſee and taſte more of him, for <hi>then ſhall we know the Lord, if we follow on to know him, Hoſe.</hi> 6. 3. we ſhall ſee him in oftner experiments, and obſerve the curioſity of his contrivements and workmanſhip in his wayes, and that is one reaſon why he crumbles his mercies to his people, and why they have his bleſſings by retaile, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156296:13"/> and trading between his people and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe may be maintained, and he more ſweetly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed: ſo the cloud empries not it ſelfe at a ſudden burſt, but diſtills and diſſolves upon the earth drop after drop.</p>
            <p>2. They ſhall receive more from him; he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures liberally backe to them that meete liberally unto him: They that will have their fill of God, muſt hold on to the looſe of a duty or ſuffering, for uſually he reſerves the beſt and fulleſt cup to the laſt; we know what <hi>Saul</hi> loſt by not holding out one moment longer, his men melted from him, the enemy was ſtrong and neere, and himſelfe had ſtayed almoſt to the end, yet for want of a minute, hee loſt by it, 1 <hi>Sam. 13. 13. Thou haſt done foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, for now would the Lord have establiſhed thy Kingdome for ever;</hi> wee know not what we loſe by making haſte, and not holding up our hands as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, to the going downe of the Sun.</p>
            <p>For the Uſe or Application of this Point,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt it meetes with the murmuring and diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who, whether out of neutrality or malignity, fulfill not after the Lord, being either purely privative in reſpect of this duty, or poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively diſaffected, of theſe we have infinite, and of divers principles, It's ſtrange, that men ſhould be no more ſenſible of the ſinne of lukewarme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but that our Saviour gives a double reaſon of it. 1. That they are not ſtone cold, that is, not ſo vitious or profane as others, for there are not ſo many degrees of cold in the lukewarme as in the cold water; but they ſhould conſider that the lukewarme are more offenſive to Chriſts ſtomack,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156296:13"/> and can leſſe be borne by it. 2. That lukewarme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is attended with ſelfe-conceit and ſecurity, <hi>thou ſaiſt I am rich and have need of nothing,</hi> but this <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 17.</note> ſecurity ariſes out of ſelfe-ignorance, by which key whoſoever is lockt up, they lye faſt. I ſhall not ſo much diſcuſſe the ſin, as the principles whence ſuch indifferency towards, or malignity againſt God and his wayes doth flow. As,</p>
            <p>1. Some are indiſpoſed meerely out of a ſtupid careleſneſſe, lying aſleepe in the ſide of our toſſed Ship in this great ſtorme, foulded faſt up in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſecurity, as blankes in a Lottery, and they are but white paper, having nothing written on them; ſuch as theſe, like <hi>Samaritans</hi> are a kin to the <hi>Iewes</hi> when the <hi>Iewes</hi> proſper, and diſclaime kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred when they goe downe, being ready to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute their eare-rings neither to golden Calfe nor Tabernacle; or haply indifferently to both, I mean Popery and purity are to them alike; And ſuch is the caſe for moſt part of ſuch poore ſoules among whom there hath beene no viſion, their Idoll ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards having made their people Idolls like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; not ſeeing, not hearing, not having any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſence; nor are they much the better who have had ſome rare Sermons, moſt what about Orders and Ceremonies, and ſuch extrinſecalls, which have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a thrum left in the loomes, to which our crafts maſters might more eaſily tye in their new peece, and if in no other, yet in this reſpect, deſerve caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; becauſe they have ſo taken up Pulpits, Pens and Tongues, as to commit waſt of pretious time, of affections between brother and brother, and even of the ſubſtance of practick godlines, which hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156296:14"/> ſuffered by ſuch diverſion; nor yet are they more awakend, whoſe Preachers have been but Ethick Lecturers reading morality, whoſe Miniſtry hath not beene firſt a fiery Serpent to ſting the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (for Gods witneſſes are called <hi>tormentors of the inhabitants of the earth</hi>) and then a pole to hold up <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 10.</note> the braſen Serpent to the wounded.</p>
            <p>2. Some are indiſpoſed to this duty of fulfilling after the Lord, out of pollicy, and that is either pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of ſafety or of temperament.</p>
            <p>1. Of ſafety, as a reede in the ſtreame, which ſtands becauſe it yeelds to the tyde and ebbe, and bends the ſame way as the ſtreame runs; the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of theſe men (as they call it) makes them ſtand as ſpectators upon the ſhore, while the Ship is toſſed at Sea, applauding themſelves alone to have hit the right blot, and cenſuring all others that endanger themſelves for the Truth; If there be deliverance they ſhall have part in the benefit without their care, coſt or trouble, and have ſhare in the winnings though they have nothing at ſtake: but put caſe a man is not agreed <hi>in hac hypotheſi,</hi> that ſuch or ſuch a cauſe is Gods, and therefore cannot lay out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in it, or ſuffer for it. I anſwer, when men are indiſpoſed towards a duty they can eaſily pleade in Barre, every leſſer ſcruple, or haeſitancy of mind, which if they might forbid the action, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more preponderating arguments, melancholy and Satan would have us at ſuch a paſſe, as wee ſhould doe little or nothing; as it is a ſinnefull thing to raviſh the judgement, to goe without, or againſt the dictate of it; ſo it is dangerous to enſlave it to baſe feares, intereſts, luſts; the heart is not more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156296:14"/> fraudulent than in ſeeking conviction, being like a Clyent inſtructing his Councell, and laying open all that favours him, concealing the ſtrength of what may be ſaid againſt him, and when a rotten heart is pitched upon a verdict like a partiall and ingaged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it will hold to it, let the evidence be what it will, reſolving to elude the evidence and not ſee it. And if inconviction of judgment, was but enough to free a man from the finne of not doing a duty, a man might the better reſt in it; but ſince it is not, let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man labour to avoid that perplexity of ſinning, if he performe, and of ſinning, if hee performe not, and to that purpoſe, not onely ſearch the Word of God, but purge his heart from the falſe byas; nor onely praying, but praying for practicke ends, <hi>He that will doe ſhall know:</hi> and let not the common ſence and concurrent judgement of thoſe that trulieſt <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 17.</note> feare God be utterly ſleighted as inconſiderable, for though that be no rule determining my act, yet it is a ſtrong motive of my more diligent inquiry. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with that of our Saviour, <hi>He that will ſave his life ſhall looſe it.</hi> It is a mans perdition to be ſafe, when he ought to periſh for God.</p>
            <p>2. Of temperament, I meane ſinfull, ſuch as are they that cry, <hi>Divide the living child,</hi> or can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to make a mixture, like the tranſplanted Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 2 King. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Who feared the Lord and ſerved their graven Images.</hi> If there be any that can goe ſo low as to give toleration to Popery (though now the Papiſts put themſelves into ſuch a poſture as they ſeeme to threaten to give, rather then take) let him conſider that wee have beene too liberall in conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence that way already, and is it not therefore <hi>that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156296:15"/> warre is in our gates;</hi> The ſetting up of <hi>Reubens</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar had preſently ſtirred up warre againſt them, if the miſpriſion had not been cleared, that no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was therein intruded; and what ſay the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <note place="margin">Judg. 5. 8.</note> of the Tribes, ſent upon the embaſſie, <hi>Rebell not againſt the Lord nor againſt us,</hi> Joſh. 22. 19. Wee ſhall ſmart for it if you doe it. Let their Popery and our Popiſhneſſe goe forth at once for ever: and ſo I would cloſe this point, but that having named the word Temperament, I would not be miſtaken, as if I meant to blow the fire which needs no bellowes, flaming already out at the houſe-top, to which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good man ſhould bring water and not oyle. For <hi>love peace,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, yea <hi>ſeeke it when it is wanting to you,</hi> yea and <hi>follow it</hi> when it is flying from you; but yet withall the ſame Scripture cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples peace and truth: peace and holineſſe in our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſeeking and following, for we ſhall have a deare bargain of it, if we ſell truth to buy it, and therefore we muſt not play booty with one another, to riſe winners, and God who hath greateſt intereſt to bee the looſer. Wee ſhould be happy in ſuch Treaeies, as might not proove a <hi>Trojan</hi>-horſe unto us; and which might heale us to the bottome, and not skin us over. And for him that delights in blood, let <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate ſanguine</hi> be his burden.</p>
            <p>3. Some are indiſpoſed to this duty out of feare, as</p>
            <p>1. Feare to be engaged, ſtanding with one foot within, and another without the threſhold, looking back-ward and forward, afraid of every new ſtep, ſaying as <hi>Caeſar</hi> at <hi>Rubicon,</hi> yet wee may goe backe, and of ſuch men there can be no certainty; for as it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156296:15"/> is ſaid of thoſe that followed <hi>Saul, they trembled af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, 1 Sam.</hi> 13. 7. and the next newes of them is that <hi>they were ſcattered from him, verſ.</hi> 11. So is it here.</p>
            <p>2. Feare of loſſe by the Reformation, and ſuch is every <hi>Demetrius,</hi> whoſe Trade goes downe by it; and therefore no wonder if all the Craftſ-men cry up their <hi>Diana;</hi> there is but little more reaſon for ingroſſers of dignities and livings in the Church, then for Monopoliſts in the State, yet let not that Oxe his mouth be muzzled that treads out the corne: If our Churches be made golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, let not candle-ruſhes be ſet up in them: If our Miniſters be Angels, they muſt have wings, and their feathers not ſo pluckt-off, as to prevent their flying; there is no colour of feare of this from a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of ſuch learning, Religion, and already decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red reſolution, for ſtarve the Nurſe, and ſhee muſt needs ſtarve the Child; the bird that is to keepe the neſt and ſit upon the egges, muſt have her meate brought in to her, and not fly abroad to purvey for herſelfe; nor makes this any thing againſt that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preaching the Goſpell, which ſome in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity or worſe doe urge as inconſiſtent with liberall maintenance; for even the Volunteer followes not the warre at his owne charges. I ſay no more but this, that poore pittances and meer benevolences, are but too like a priſoners maintenance, whoſe ſmall allowance, and almes-basket to boot, keep him ſtill hungry.</p>
            <p>3. Feare or hatred of the purity of Ordinances and power of Religion, of which thouſands will ſay, as they of Chriſt, <hi>Mal. 3. 2. But who may abide
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156296:16"/> the day of his comming, and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth, for hee is like a Refiners fire and Fullers ſope.</hi> This root bears gall and wormewood, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 18. unto ſuch the burning and ſhining light of the Miniſtery is terrible; and the more, when they ſhall not be able at pleaſure to hamper it in the old ſnare of Ceremonies, or bring upon it the old extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhers with that facility as was wont; it is a marke of a <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> if the Arke of God ſmite him with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merods and afflicts him, it ſerves not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſo.</p>
            <p>4. A ſcrupulous feare of ſinning againſt authority, and in truth the tenderneſſe of the conſcience in that point is to be approved; for God hath ſo hedged in Magiſtracy, <hi>whether the ſupreame or ſubordinate,</hi> that <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 13, 14.</note> whoſoever breakes through that hedge, ſhall feele the thornes in his ſides, and therefore conſcience muſt acquit it ſelfe of it's warrant and ſincerity, that it ſeekes nothing but the ſaving of the Ship and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter from the violence of the ſtorme; and in that caſe that once ſpeaking Aſſe ſaid reaſon, who having ſaved her ſelfe, yea and ſaved her Maſter from the Sword, againſt his owne will, did thus plead againſt his anger, <hi>What have I done unto thee, that thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 22. 28, 30.</note> 
               <hi>hast ſmitten me, was I ever wont to doe ſo before time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this point helpe forward our Humiliation this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> day, for our not following the Lord fully, and is it not time, when our former rebellions againſt and provocations of God, doe now plead againſt us by the firſt of Gods foure ſore judgements, the Sword, and that Sword the ſoreſt of all Swords, which kind <note place="margin">Ezek. 14 21.</note> may yet doubtleſſe be caſt out by Prayer and Faſting:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156296:16"/> nor ſhall I now at this time ſet in order before you our former Nationall ſinnes, for which God hath been a <hi>Moth</hi> unto us, and is now become a <hi>Lion;</hi> for from ſo ſmall a thing as a <hi>Moth,</hi> doth he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be a <hi>Lion</hi> unto <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Hoſ. 5. 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us rather apply our ſelves to take notice of ſuch markes of Gods diſpleaſure as are now upon us, ſince we came to the borders of our happineſſe, and obſerve the reaſon why wee are wafted from the ſhore ſo farre into the maine backe againe. When was the venome ſpirits of men ſo diſcovered as now of latter times, <hi>When I would have healed</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the ſinne of</hi> Ephraim <hi>was diſcovered,</hi> Hoſ. 7. 1. Healing times are diſcovering times; and have wee not cauſe to looke for that in <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 24. 20. namely that the Lord ſhould <hi>turne to doe us hurt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume us after hee hath done us good;</hi> or for that in <hi>Numb. 14. 34. Yee ſhall know my breach of promiſe;</hi> Our Arke is like <hi>Noahs</hi> floating upon the waters. We have many <hi>that are weeping for Tammuz,</hi> thirſting <note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 14.</note> for the returne of their <hi>Adonis,</hi> we have bitter mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings and eructations of gall againſt God and his Truth, we feare our remedies; wee are full of diviſions, ſinfull, paenall in Church and State. We abound in jealouſies, a juſt puniſhment of our provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God to jealouſie of us by our former dalliances with ſuperſtition. <hi>Wee arc diſcouraged becauſe of the way, and ſpeake againſt God and</hi> Moſes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. 4, 5. and therefore hath the Lord <hi>ſent fiery Serpents amongst us,</hi> that bite us and even devoure us, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is torne into diviſions and fragments, the ſwarm is up and ſettles in ſo many places, as without great mercy, they will never be got into one hive; ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156296:17"/> ſymptomes doe wee put forth now that God is healing of us, and are come to ſuch a <hi>criſis</hi> as makes our hearts to bleed, what is there in <hi>Ireland?</hi> what in <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>pila minantia pilis? quis talia fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do?</hi> What monſter of cruelty can endure to ſee his Mothers bowels ſo tipt up. Where are our publicke ſpirits remote from mixture of private ends? What Souldier is willing to forget his <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ream meſsem,</hi> or golden harveſt, and rather be bankrupt by peace, then make the State bankerupt by warre? What Delinquent rather offers up himſelfe to Tryall, and <note place="margin">Iona. 1. 12</note> ſaith, <hi>Take me up and caſt me forth into the Sea, ſo ſhall the Sea be calme unto you?</hi> Surely God will ferch our pride out of us by ſtrong hand, if wee take not off the head of it, and caſt it over the wall, to prevent his indignation; and yet wee have marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous mercies too, if we had eyes to ſee them. God hath evidently ſhowne that he is in our burning-buſh, we had otherwiſe been in aſhes by this time, and ſo we are like the flint betweene the hard hammer and the ſoſt pillow, and have cauſe of the beſt kind of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, which is <hi>to love and weepe,</hi> as that woman did: if we be not battered into the mould, why are we not melted, that we may runne into it? and let theſe humiliations be continued in their vigour, that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency beget not formality; for <hi>the valley of Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2 15. <hi>Vſe</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>is given to us for a doore of hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it ſet an edge upon you to fullfill after the Lord.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. When hee goes before you, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>2. When he flyes from you, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. When the Lord goes before you and invites
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156296:17"/> you yet after him, by making the tracke of his feet evident; we muſt not ſit ſtill, when his Cloud ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to move forward, it's ſafe to march after it: and ſurely if God be to be ſeene. 1. In nickes of time, <hi>Tanquam a machina.</hi> 2. In working or creating good out of evill, hope out of deſpaire, furtherances out of oppoſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. In ſeaſonable diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Clouds, while they were but like a mans hand. 4. In miniſtring or ſuggeſting timely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes or preventions. 5. In entangling the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in their owne webb, or bringing downe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by their owne hands. 6. In drawing hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bleſſings on, upon their way above our firſt thoughts or aime, as he drew on <hi>Luther,</hi> whetted by importunity of Adverſaries; then is God gone out before us, wee may ſee his foot-ſtepps in all theſe wayes, therefore follow him.</p>
            <p>2. When he flies from you, yet then follow him fully: Doth he hide his face, delay to heare, leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our danger, are things in worſe ſtate with us ſince <hi>Moſes</hi> came? are Treaties abortive, Faſts imprevalent? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let us not turne backe and ſay, <hi>This evill is from the Lord, why ſhould we wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him any longer?</hi> There is reaſon that God ſhould be ſharpe, we have inveterate ſtaines to be waſht out, which will hardly be got out, untill the cloth be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rub'd to peeces: Chriſt came with a ſhaking of the Heavens and Earth, and all the Nations, <hi>Hag.</hi> 6. 7. after ſuch concuſſions, <hi>The deſire of all Nations ſhall come;</hi> nor did Chriſt riſe out of his grave without an Earth-quake, <hi>cum duplicantur late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res venit Moſes;</hi> for how could mercies be wonders, if ſtraits were not wondrous; though obſtructions
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156296:18"/> be obſtinate, yet Chriſt will come in to his people, even when <hi>the doores are ſhut:</hi> preſently after <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> bitter waters, God brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Elim,</hi> where they had twelve wels of water, and threeſcore and ten Palme-trees, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 27. God hides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſought, delayeth to be importuned, flies from us to be followed.</p>
            <p>I will adde but a word or two of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To all.</item>
               <item>2. To you our Honourable Senatours.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. That which I ſhall ſay to all is this, that if we fulfill after the Lord, we ſhall cut ſhorter our travailes and troubles: ſo had this people done if they had followed the Lord fully at this time, we lengthen our miſeries by ſhortening of our duties, and the Lord keepes aloofe from us, becauſe we lye aloofe from him: God is diſabled from doing great workes among us by out diſtruſt, <hi>Hee could doe no great workes among them, becauſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe,</hi> ſaith the Text: Or admit we be long holden off our happineſſe, as <hi>Caleh</hi> was kept out of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes fill our laps at the laſt; the longer day God takes to make payment, the more he gives us at the laſt. If he come not to heale <hi>Lazarus</hi> while he is alive, we ſhall loſe nothing by it, for he will come to raiſe him when he is dead; therefore let us fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him fully, both by prayer, and all poſſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions to his worke, and cauſe, and Goſpell; what if we have not an eare-ring left, ſo that the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle have it: water we ſee puts it ſelfe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and contrary to particular nature, riſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156296:18"/> 
               <hi>ad prohibendum vacuum,</hi> to prevent a fraction in the univerſe; who is likely to ſave his own cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, when the Ship founders; but it may be the worke ſtickes, and it may be at thee, why is not thy ſhoulder at the wheele, when the Cart is ſtalled; though <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtick at firſt in <hi>Egipt,</hi> yet they went out at length with the <hi>Egyptians</hi> leave, <hi>and not a dog</hi> (as <note place="margin">Exo. 11. 7</note> the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith) <hi>moved his tongue againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. To you of Senatorian order, be you encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to follow the Lord fully, and let not the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of the higheſt Orbe be ſloweſt of motion, you have need of encouragements, that you may ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the obloquies, the ſcandalls, ſuſpitions, jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies had of you, and endure the contradiction of ſuch as are afraid to be healed: In the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities they complaine their muſes lye a dying, O let it never be by or under your hand, but onely teach them as of old they were feigned, ſo now really to frequent and be miſtreſſes of purer fountaines: Some cry out that Religion will be changed, and that there will be an alteration thereof; If this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ariſe from this, that the ceremonies and uſages hitherto offenſive and burdenſome, are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be aboliſht, what can be ſaid more againſt them; for is it not time to caſt them out, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe they are accounted ſuch immoveables, that to remove them, is to commit waſte upon the very free-hold it ſelfe. It's time to breake the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent, and to call it <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> a peece of braſſe, when it's idolized; or if rather the quarrell ariſe from that pure adminiſtration of Ordinances of worſhip which is deſired, is it not as voide of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for ſhall perfective alterations be accounted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156296:19"/> deſtructive, doth the changing of the Tabernacle into a Temple, wherein are ten Candleſticks for one and more ſetledneſſe and beauty, imply any change of Religion? Others finde out as many Religions as we have Articles of Doctrine, nine and thirty, and upbraide us with Sects and Schiſmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which truely are our miſery, and fill us with ſcandalls, ſhame and ſorrow; yet this I may ſay, that if every ſeverall or new opinion, makes a new Religion, then we have more then ſo many: If not, then doubtleſſe we have fewer; but whatſoever it be, it is but a fond thing to ſay there will be no building, becauſe the timber, ſtone, materialls lye yet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed heapes. I beſeech you to ſet on worke hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Mountaines, and ſtone-ſquarers, to prepare <note place="margin">1 Kin. 5. 15, 18.</note> timber and ſtones to build the Temple, that our <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> may at length be a City compact together, and at unity in it ſelfe. And as for all aſperſions and reflections upon you, follow the Lord fully; and as the ecclipſed Moone by keeping her motion, wades out of the ſhadow, and recovers her ſplendor, ſo ſhall you, <hi>For every tongue that ſhall riſe in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa 54. 17</note> 
               <hi>againſt thee thou ſhalt condemne, and this is the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage of the ſervants of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the confirming of you in following after the Lord, I might put you in minde, what Gods people have done for God in preſſing extremities. namely,</p>
            <p>1. Doing that which ſaving the preſſing caſe, it might be queſtioned whether they ought; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof we have in <hi>Phinehas, Numb.</hi> 25. 13. who by an act of zeale, turned away the neere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching wrath from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>made an attonement
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156296:19"/> for them,</hi> by ſuch a ſacrifice as it's doubted by what warrant he offered it up, I meane the execution of Delinquents, and yet is juſtified and highly extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by God for it. And ſo <hi>Eſther,</hi> in a time of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, put herſelf to do that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>which was not according</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 4. 16</note> 
               <hi>to the Law,</hi> to draw forth her people out of deſtined deſtruction; nor doe I know how ſhe could have anſwered it to God, if her particular obſervation of that humane Law, had forbidden her thereſcue and preſervation of a whole Nation of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yet the Law ſhe broke was capitall, as ſhe ſaith, <hi>Ver.</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. and therefore ſhe goes on with this reſolution, <hi>If I periſh I periſh;</hi> whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, ſhe could in this caſe have comfortably pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht in the breach of that known Law.</p>
            <p>2. Standing to it, ſo as it might be queſtioned whether it was needfull, and it is the caſe of <hi>Daniel, Cap.</hi> 6. 10. whoſe keeping his thrice a day devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and opening his windowes towards <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not abating of the number of his prayers, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them in a more concealed manner, to have avoided the malice of his accuſers for one Moneths time (for no longer was the Interdict to laſt) may ſeeme more then needs; yet he did not budge a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot, nor abate a circumſtance, becauſe he ſaw his Religion was ſtricken at, and his ſincerity put to the tryall, which he was reſolved to maintaine with (as I may ſo ſpeake) a holy obſtinacy, whatſoever came on it. I doe not urge theſe examples, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate any man unto raſhneſſe, eſpecially in caſes not thus circumſtanciated, but to ſhew how fully they went after the Lord, in that wherein carnall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might and would have found ſundry ſpecious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156296:20"/> eluſions to have evaded the duty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall reſume the exhortation in a few words, as touching your advancing and ſetling Gods intereſt, and then he will ſettle yours; <hi>He tooke out of all the Cities</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Text) the high places and Images,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 14 5.</note> 
               <hi>and the Kingdome was quiet before him:</hi> If you will build God a houſe, he will make you an houſe; as it was ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> labour ye therefore to ſet up the evangelicall worſhip and regiment of Chriſt, ſo as there may not be one <hi>howbeit,</hi> if poſſible, as there was in that of <hi>Aſa, Howbeit the high places were not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 20 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>taken away;</hi> which worke we ſhall bring to beſt perfection, if we adhere to the word of God, and print after ſuch an originall as went before all edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of error: not that I would tye any man to ſuch examples, cuſtomes, conſtitutions of the word, as were meerely occaſionall in their both riſe and uſe, and reſpective to times then being, for what would that differ from a ſuperſtitious valuing of the braſen Serpent, after the uſe of it was out, becauſe it once had inſtitution of God; but of this point no more now: My buſineſſe is, to excite you to follow the Cloud, and the Rock ſhall follow you; let ſeeds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be ſent forth into all our fields, that the people may be taken by the conſcience, and not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Law, for the ſtrength and continuance of a reformation, lyes not all in the Magiſtrate, but in this, that the people receive the truth into them and among them, who otherwiſe will be but as Hens in a coope, alwayes boaking to get out: which was the reaſon that they were ſo up and downe in <hi>Iudah,</hi> according as they had remiſſe or religious Princes; and by this meanes alſo ſhall Popery be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156296:20"/> profligate, and Papiſts converted a little better, then meerely by oath of ſupremacy and allegiance, which breed ſuch a generation as is contrary to rule of Philoſophy, which is, <hi>Generatio unius eſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio alterius,</hi> whereas theſe new Proteſtants are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſtill.</p>
            <p>Finally, If there be ſome croſſe ſprings in the locke, ſome propheſie may lye againſt our preſent hopes, for God hath his <hi>arcana Imperij;</hi> or if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of times, unripeneſſe of the people, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard the worke, ſo as it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>ſo many yeares was this Temple in building,</hi> yet I ſay to you as the Lord to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Chro. 6. 8. <hi>Thou didst well that it was in thine heart:</hi> and let but a right ſpirit (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſpirit of adherence unto, and acquieſſence in God) carry you on to fulfill after him, and then, though <hi>Caleb</hi> through the peoples rebellion, wander in the wilderneſſe forty yeares, and be kept off his promiſed reward; yet he ſhall come into poſſeſſion thereof at laſt, <hi>and his ſeede ſhall inherit it,</hi> and ſo I ſhould come to that which remaines in the words, as namely, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To follow the Lord fully proceeds from another ſpirit,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>than the unbeleeving Iſraelites are acted withall:</hi> and this ſpirit of <hi>Caleb</hi> was clearly that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cals a <hi>ſpirit of Faith,</hi> in cloſing with, and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto God alone. I cannot particularly handle this point, only be bold to caſt in a word or two towards the ſetting of the byas right way, els a man may run and never obaine. If we would have the hand of the dyall to point and goe right without, the wheeles and poyſes muſt be right within, and wee muſt not onely looke at the worke we have to doe, but alſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156296:21"/> to the principle within us, that it be a right ſpirit, for there is no queſtion but that a man of no filiall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition towards God, may be Gods toole or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or (if ye will) Gods ſervant, to performe ſuch or ſuch a ſervice right in Gods ſight, I ſhall not need to ſhew how farre a man may goe, and what adventure he may make in a good cauſe upon other reaſons, principles and motives than proceed from a Goſpell ſpirit; <hi>Cyrus</hi> proclaimes liberty to the Church, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. yet was he a man <hi>that knew not the Lord.</hi> I doubt not but a Proteſtant upon a dogmaticall Faith or beleefe of his tenets and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, might among Papiſts dye upon them, and yet come farre ſhort of ſalvation; how farre would the name of <hi>Abraham</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> have carried a Jew, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a <hi>Iew in letter?</hi> Martyrdome is no merit.</p>
            <p>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t every man therefore <hi>take heed to his ſpirit that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>he deale not treacherouſly,</hi> for howſoever your good ſervice periſhes not to the Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, yet it periſhes to you, if you be not carried with hearts full of God. Many a man is a Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to build <hi>Noah</hi> an Arke, wherein himſelfe is not ſaved. There are many reſt in their meere oppoſition to, and hate of Popery, as if that ſhould ſeale up their ſalvation; and many againe will reaſon thus, The cauſe wherein I am is good, it will ſwim out it's gods, and that is their plea. Alas this is not all, for be the Proteſtant truth never ſo cleere to thee, and be the cauſe thou art in never ſo good, yet thou mayeſt be loſt in it, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were loſt while they went in the ſame path, wherein the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſaved; therefore pray and ſeeke for ſuch a ſpirit of chuſing and following the Lord thy God,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:156296:21"/> as may enſoule thy actions or outward works; and then beſide the acceptance and teſtimony thy wayes ſhall find with God, thou ſhalt be able to goe through, and fulfill after the Lord, which a man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on naturall parts, and ſtrength of morall principles or vertues, ſhall never doe, <hi>for youths ſhall faint and be weary, and young m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhall utterly fall,</hi> Iſa. 40. 30. that is, men of moſt able ſelfe-ſufficiencies, who though their motion was ſwift before, yet when they come to the center of their own ends, they reſt and proceed no farther; ſuch a ſpirit therefore as <hi>Caleb</hi> had, doe you reſtleſly ſeeke of God the giver of it <hi>to them that aske him,</hi> that being ſincerely carried, (which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in great and glorious actions is the more hard) you may reape the <hi>Euge</hi> of your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is better then the <hi>Hic eſt</hi> of all the world; and not only ſo, but there will be more hope of the worke when it is carried on by ſuch hearts; as God ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> he was a man after his own heart, and what followes, <hi>He ſhall fulfill all my will, Act.</hi> 13. 22. And of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> it is ſaid, that in every worke that he began in the ſervice of the houſe of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandements, to ſeeke his God, <hi>hee did it with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron, 31. 21.</note> 
               <hi>all his heart, and proſpered;</hi> ſuch hearts, ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe we pray to them that are now ingaged in this great worke, that ſo promiſes with the entayle of them upon Poſterity may follow ſuch <hi>Calebs</hi> for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
